Register of the Ellery W. Stone papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ellery W. Stone papers
1911-1981
87008
Hoover Institution Archives
11 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (6.71 linear feet)
The Ellery W. Stone papers contain correspondence, speeches and writings, reminiscences, orders, memoranda, reports, personnel records, printed matter, and photographs relating to Allied occupation policy in Italy during and after World War II and to the development of radio and other telecommunication systems.
Stone, Ellery W. (Ellery Wheeler), 1894-1981
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Henry F. (Henry Francis) Grady typescript: Adventures in diplomacy, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1894 January 14 Born, Oakland, California
1913-1914 Majored in electrical and radio engineering, University of California
1914-1917 Assistant U.S. Radio Inspector, Department of Commerce, San Francisco
1917-1919 District Communications Superintendent, 12th Naval District, U.S. Naval Radio Station, San Diego
1919 General Manager, Moorhead Laboratories and Lee de Forest, Inc.
1919 Author, Elements of Radiotelegraphy
1922 Manager, Radio Department of the Pacific States
1924-1931 President, Federal Telegraph Company of California, which was acquired by International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation (ITT) in 1931
1931-1968 Joined ITT after merger and held various executive positions
1943 Vice President of Communications, Allied Control Commission for Italy
1944 Promoted to Rear Admiral
1944-1947 Chief Commissioner, Allied Control Commission in Italy and Chief Civil Affairs Officer, Allied Military Government in Italy
1946-1948 Regional Vice President for Middle East and Cairo, ITT
1948-1949 President, Federal Telephone & Radio Corporation
1948-1968 Director, ITT
1950-1958 President, American Cable & Radio Corporation and subsidiaries
1958 Retired from the Navy
1961-1965 President, ITT Europe
1969 Retired from ITT
1981 September 18 Died, Montclair, New Jersey
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Ellery W. Stone contain correspondence, speeches and writings, reminiscences, orders, memoranda, reports, personnel records, printed matter, and photographs relating to Allied occupation policy in Italy during and after World War II and to the development of radio and other telecommunication systems.
Throughout his life, Stone was involved in the radio and communications field. His interest in electronics was sparked by the gift of a battery-powered motor on his 14th birthday, and during his career he held several executive positions at the International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation (ITT). The Biographical and Personal File contains interviews documenting Stone's career in the communications field, as well as his work with the Allied Commission in Italy. This file also includes correspondence related to a book written by two reporters for Tempo called Finally the Allies Speak and citations for various awards that Stone received. The Radio and Communications File includes materials concerning organizations where Stone was a member, such as the Society of Wireless Pioneers and the De Forest Pioneers, as well as printed material, including publications with biographical articles on Stone. An article detailing Stone's career can be found in the Oversize Materials series.
The majority of the material in the Allied Commission and United States Navy File, which documents Stone's Navy career, relates to the Allied Commission in Italy. Several folders in this series, such as the cable and wireless service file, contain an index with a summary of included documents. Also included is the typescript Secret Story of One Month of Reign, which examines the reign of Umberto II, the abdication of Victor Emmanuel III, and Stone's role in these events as the Chief Commissioner of the Allied Commission. The Photographs and Oversize Materials series contain photographs from Stone's military service.
The Speeches and Writings series includes bound blueprint sheets of Stone's book Elements of Radiotelegraphy, which started as a series of lectures, as well as his speeches on communication and farewell address after completing his service with the Allied Commission.
Source: Oral-History: Ellery W. Stone. IEEE Global History Network. http://www.ieeeghn.org/wiki/index.php/Oral-History:Ellery_W._Stone
Allied Commission.; Italy--History--Allied occupation, 1943-1947.; Military government.; Radio.; Telecommunication.; United States. Navy--Officers.; World War, 1939-1945--Italy.
- Biographical and Personal File, 1911-1981 (Boxes 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence, clippings, interviews, and curriculum vitae, arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Arlington National Cemetery file, 1965-circa 1967 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Includes map to grave of Behn.
  - Awards
    - General, 1944-1965 (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
    - Distinguished Service Medal, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Knight Commander, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Légion d'Honneur, 1963, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 6)
      Includes speeches by Stone and photographs.
  - Bancroft Library and Plate of Brass artifact, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Biographical information, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Citations and commendations, 1945-1947, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
    Includes message from Harry Truman.
  - Clippings
    - Biographical articles, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
      See also: Oversize Materials.
    - Death of Flora Pickering Stone, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Marriage and religious conversion, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Obituary, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Promotions, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 1: 14)
      See also: Allied Commission and United States Navy File, clippings.
    - Youth, 1911, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1979 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1934 (Box-folder 1: 17)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 1: 18-19)
      - 1946 (Box-folder 1: 20)
      - 1947 (Box-folder 2: 1)
      - 1948 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      - 1964 (Box-folder 2: 3)
      - 1967 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - 1968 (Box-folder 2: 5)
      - 1979-1981 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Congratulations, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1940-1981 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Drawing depicting Ellery Stone, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Finally the Allies Speak by Luigi Romersa and Bonaventura Caloro
    - Clippings, 1961, undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1968 (Box-folder 2: 11-12)
  - Holiday cards, undated (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Interview of Stone as told to A. J. Schmitt (ITT Corporate History Interviews), 1978 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    Includes typescript and notes.
  - Interview of Stone by Arthur L. Norberg, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Invitations, 1946, undated (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Menu, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Moon landing stamps, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    Includes Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong signatures.
  - Navy identification card photocopy, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Radio operator licenses, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Society for French American Cultural Services and Educational Aid, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Tax correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Wedding announcement list, undated (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - "The Wizards of Electricity" playbill, undated (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Miscellany, 1967-1977, undated (Box-folder 2: 25)
- Allied Commission and United States Navy File, 1942-1969 (Boxes 3-7)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, printed matter, memoranda, and personnel records, arranged alphabetically by subject or format. See also: Declassified U.S. Government Records.
  - Accounts of supplies furnished to Italy by Allies, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Advances to Allied Forces (Lire advances), 1946 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Anti-inflation file, 1944-1946, undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Bonomi, Ivanoe speech excerpt, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Cable and wireless service file, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 3: 5-7)
    Includes index.
  - Clippings, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 3: 8-10)
    Includes clippings about Stone.
  - Clippings, miscellaneous, 1944-1976, undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Commissions certificates, 1925-1949 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1943-1944 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1944-1945 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - 1946 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1947 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - 1950-1969 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Directive for Armistice Control Commission, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Directory of veterans of Allied Control Commission and Allied Military Government, 1954 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Forrestal Diaries, correspondence and reports, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Forrestal, James, speech, 1949 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Index of miscellaneous Allied Control Commission papers, undated (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Memoranda
    - Future policy toward Italy, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - Memorandum for President Truman, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 15)
      See also: memoranda and correspondence file.
    - Military situation, undated (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Memoranda and correspondence file, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    Includes memorandum for President Truman.
  - Moscow communiqué, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Naval Reserve file, 1953-1961 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Navy posters, undated (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Note cards, undated (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Notes from interview with King Victor Emmanuel III, 1944 February 5 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Notes on conversation between Stone and Prime Minister Parri, 1945 June 19 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Official Navy file of Admiral Stone, 1945-1959 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Official Navy file of Admiral Stone (cont'd.), 1945-1959 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Organization and reorganization of Allied Commission file, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
  - Organization chart, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Personnel file, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Personnel file, completion of service and relief, 1944-1947, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Press headlines and radio bulletins, 1947 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Printed matter
    - "The Allied Armies in Italy From 3rd September, 1943 to 12th December, 1944," Supplement to the London Gazette, 1950 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - "Allied Military Government of Rome Under the Fifth Army," report by Edgar E. Hume, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Documenti relative ai rapporti tra l'Italia e le Nazioni Unite, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - The Renaissance of Religion in Science - An Inroad into Communism by Roland T. E. Bowler, typescript, 1958 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - Review of Allied Military Government and of the Allied Commission in Italy, undated (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - "Salerno-Naples. February-March 1944," by T. G. Bergin, 1947 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - Schio Massacre, 1948 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Summary of Regulations Governing the Issuance and Wearing of Decorations, Medals and Ribbons Now Designated for Naval Personnel, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Weekly Bulletin of the Allied Commission
      For Volume 1, see: Declassified U.S. Government Records.
      - Volume 2, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 6: 3)
      - Volume 3, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - Loose newsletters, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - United States Naval Institute Proceedings, 1934 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - 1944-1945 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Promotions and appointments, 1943-1945, undated (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Review of Allied Commission achievements and communications work, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Secret Story of One Month of Reign, Italia-Nuova series, annotated typescript
    - Volume 1, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - Volume 2, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - Volume 3, 1947 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Senate Committee Investigating the National Defense Program," draft notes, 1945 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Speech (broadcast) "Allied Military Government in Italy,", undated (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - United States Naval Institute certificate of membership, 1944 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Miscellany, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 7: 5)
- Radio and Communications File, 1937-1980 (Boxes 7-8)
  Includes printed matter and correspondence, arranged alphabetically by subject or format.
  - Clippings, 1934-1972 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1972 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - De Forest Pioneers file, 1975-1978, undated (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Electronics in the West: The First Fifty Years by Jane Morgan, correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - ITT Europe file, 1965, undated (Box-folder 7: 10)
    Includes photographs.
  - Printed matter
    - Bell Laboratories Record, 1950 (Box-folder 7: 11)
    - "Brief History of Marconi Wireless Telegraph Company" by Thorn Mayes, undated (Box-folder 7: 12)
    - "Brief History of the United Wireless Telegraph Company" by Thorn Mayes, undated (Box-folder 7: 13)
    - International System News, 1933 (Box-folder 7: 14)
      Includes article about Stone.
    - "The Origins of the Electronics Industry on the Pacific Coast" by Arthur L. Norberg, 1976 (Box-folder 7: 15)
    - "Radio Ancestors - An Autobiography" by Robert H. Marriott, 1968 (Box-folder 7: 16)
    - The Story of Kolster Radio, 1928 (Box-folder 7: 17)
      Includes biography of Stone.
    - When Telecom and ITT Were Young by Maurice Deloraine, 1976 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Resignation, 1964 (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Sarnoff, David file, 1937-1953 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Society of Wireless Pioneers
    - Honorary membership, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    - Life membership, 1980, undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - Newsletter, 1972 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - Sparks: Tales of the Wireless Pioneers, Volume 3, 1974 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - Yearbook and directory, 1976 (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - Miscellany, 1975, undated (Box-folder 8: 7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1918-1967 (Box 9)
  Includes speeches, articles, and correspondence, arranged chronologically. See also: Biographical and Personal File, Awards, Légion d'Honneur.
  - Assignments for correspondence course in elementary radio, undated (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Elements of Radiotelegraphy, bound volumes, 1918 (Box-folder 9: 2-3)
  - "Communication System for the Italian Squadron Transatlantic Flight," Electrical Communication, 1934 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - "Communications for Italian Transatlantic Flight,", 1934 August (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - "Communications for Byrd Antarctic Expedition II,", 1936 February (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Speech on President Roosevelt's death for Radio Roma, 1945 April 13 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    Includes Italian text.
  - Statement on the death of President Roosevelt, 1945 April 13 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Farewell address, Allied Commission, 1947 March 14 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - "Communications -- Lifeline of World Peace, Trade and Economy," New York Trade Week World Trade Luncheon, 1952 May 21
    - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 9: 10)
    - Program and report, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 9: 11)
    - Speech, 1952 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - "International Communications: Past and Future," New York Chapter of Armed Forces Communications and Electronics Association, 1960 November 30
    - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 9: 13)
    - Speech, typescript, 1960 (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - "Policy of ITT Towards Europe," conference commemorating the 20th Anniversary of the Marshall Plan, 1967 June 7 (Box-folder 9: 15)
- Photographs, 1944-1946 (Box 10)
  Consists of prints and negatives, arranged alphabetically by subject or format.
  - Art prints (Giranello and Manacero), undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Award ceremonies
    - Stone presents awards, 1945, undated (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - Stone receives a medal, undated (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Boca Raton, Florida, undated (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Caserma Carabinieri (Stone with W. D. Morgan, Sac, Mtousa), 1945 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Civilian relief with Colonel O. J. Bizzozero and Stone examining supplies, 1944 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Comic, undated (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - House, undated (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - House Military Affairs Committee, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Negatives, undated (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Navy photographs, 1945, undated (Box-folder 10: 11-13)
  - Personal photographs and holiday cards, undated (Box-folder 10: 14)
  - Photos from book, undated (Box-folder 10: 15)
    Includes negatives.
  - Portrait of Stone, undated (Box-folder 10: 16)
  - Princess Marie José of Savoy with children, undated (Box-folder 10: 17)
  - Stone and Prime Minister Ivanoe Bonomi examine civilian relief supplies, Rome, 1944 (Box-folder 10: 18)
  - Stone welcomes Mathew B. Ridgway, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 19)
  - Stone with Bruno Romani, undated (Box-folder 10: 20)
  - Stone with Field Marshall Harold Alexander, 1945, undated (Box-folder 10: 21)
  - Stone with Herbert Hoover and others, 1946 (Box-folder 10: 22)
  - Stone with H. M. Ziroli, Brigadier Lush and others, 1946 (Box-folder 10: 23)
  - V-E Day services, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 24)
  - Wedding, undated (Box-folder 10: 25)
  - Miscellany, 1946, undated (Box-folder 10: 26)
- Oversize Materials, 1943-1979 (Boxes 11-12)
  Includes photo albums, mounted stars, article on Stone, and cartoon of Stone.
  - Mounted stars, undated (Box 11)
  - Sparks Journal with article "The Unique Career of Ellery W. Stone,", circa 1979 (Box 12)
  - Cartoon of Stone, undated (Box 12)
  - Photo albums of General Command of the Carabinieri Reali (Royal Carabiniers)
    - Marshal H. R. Alexander, 1945 (Box 12)
    - General Morgan, 1943 (Box 12)
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1942-1945 (Box 13)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfiled, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2016 March release of records, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 13: 1-5)
    Correspondence, printed matter, and photographs relating to Stone's work with the Allied Commission and United States Navy. Includes Volume 1 of Weekly Bulletin of the Allied Commission and a draft of Allied Military Administration of Italy, 1943-1945 by C. R. S. Harris.